<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>videotalks on Diego J.'s Software Tar Pit</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/tags/videotalks/</link><description>Recent content in videotalks on Diego J.'s Software Tar Pit</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><managingEditor>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-L贸pez)</managingEditor><webMaster>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-L贸pez)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/tags/videotalks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Progress towards and engineering discipline of software by Mary Shaw</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/2015-08-14-progress-towards-an-engineering-discipline-of-software/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-L贸pez)</author><guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/2015-08-14-progress-towards-an-engineering-discipline-of-software/</guid><description>Several days ago, I watched this videotalk of Mary Shaw that tried to give an answer to the question is Software Engineering an Engineering discipline yet?
Dr. Shaw makes a parallelism with Civil Engineering that started as a empirical discipline and, thanks to strong scientific foundations, evolved to what we could call full engineering.
Software Engineering is not there yet. It needs more work and professionalization. Many of the so-called Software Engineers have no software engineering knowledge and/or skills and therefore software disasters happens.</description></item><item><title>Real software architecture</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/2015-03-03-real-software-architecture/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-L贸pez)</author><guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/2015-03-03-real-software-architecture/</guid><description>Simon Brown is an independent software consultant from Jersey (UK) and gave this talk about Software Architecture in GOTO Amsterdam 2014.
This talk delights me in several ways. First, Simon show us several common problems that happens in many software companies: diagrams of the software are not synchronized with code because. That is, we design some type of software architecture but we don&amp;rsquo;t follow our own path when coding.</description></item></channel></rss>