<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Project Management on Diego J.&#39;s Software Tar Pit</title>
    <link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/tags/project-management/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Project Management on Diego J.&#39;s Software Tar Pit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <managingEditor>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/tags/project-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Project saboteurs</title>
      <link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/2016/02/project-saboteurs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</author>
      <guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/2016/02/project-saboteurs/</guid>
      <description>Introduction You have just been appointed leader of a new fascinating project. Hard years working in boring tasks have paid off. You are excited before your big day: your first meeting with your client (the owner of the business) and some other stakeholders (managers and other employees of the business).
Sabotage So the meeting starts. Relationship with the business owner is smooth and you begin to write notes about software requirements, current system limitations, technologies&amp;hellip; You know that you&amp;rsquo;ll have more than enough information to make the first requirement document.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agile project management</title>
      <link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/2016/01/agile-project-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</author>
      <guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/2016/01/agile-project-management/</guid>
      <description>Software Engineering is a special type of Engineering During too much time Software Engineering has been molded as a traditional Engineering, with the same terms and ideas that came from this disciplines. But they failed.
Firstly, Software Engineering has an immaterial final product. It is not a bridge, a road, or a mine for example. Thus, software engineers works with ideas more than anything else.
Thus, traditional engineers are limited by Physics laws while software engineers are only limited by the computational model they use and by the power of the machines their software run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing clients</title>
      <link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/2015/07/managing-clients/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</author>
      <guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/2015/07/managing-clients/</guid>
      <description>The Players It&amp;rsquo;s not a secret that software engineers prefer a clean and completed specification than metting with clients.
We tend to think that meetings are a waste of time and many of our colleagues are not very fond of what is called soft skills.
On the other side, we have some clients that have no idea about software and want the changes in their platform now.
What is all of that?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>