<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>culture on Diego J.'s Software Tar Pit</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/tags/culture/</link><description>Recent content in culture on Diego J.'s Software Tar Pit</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><managingEditor>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</managingEditor><webMaster>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/tags/culture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to work in a toxic environment</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2025/09/how-to-work-in-a-toxic-environment/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</author><guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2025/09/how-to-work-in-a-toxic-environment/</guid><description>How to work in a toxic environment There are many posts about growing a good culture of empathy in teams. But how could you deal with a toxic culture? In this post we are going to delve into this question.
Toxic behaviors What is a toxic environment? A toxic environment is one where the bad behaviors are not corrected or they are ignored.
As simple as that. There are people doing things that affect negatively to others, and nobody is correcting them.</description></item><item><title>Remote work</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2025/08/remote-work/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</author><guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2025/08/remote-work/</guid><description>Remote work In this post I would like to voice my opinion about remote work.
Introduction Remote work grew a lot in the 2020 because of the COVID-19 pandemic, but now it has started to being seen as diminishing from the corporate world. Less and less remote positions, more in-office requirements, and more one-sided conversations about the benefits of in-person work, or blaming remote workers for slacking or being simply lazy (as if there weren’t people who go to the office and do nothing all day).</description></item><item><title>Everybody has value</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2025/08/everybody-has-value/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</author><guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2025/08/everybody-has-value/</guid><description>Everybody has value In this post I tell a war story that happened during my time in a medium-sized multi-national company where I had a leadership role.
Introduction Working there I had a good developer in my team with some physical disabilities (vision related). Others hand the idea that they were frustrated in their day-to-day role, and indeed it looked like they were.
This developer felt not being used at their 100% capacity, and consequently, they felt undervalued.</description></item><item><title>Do what the community does</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2023/12/do-what-the-community-does/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-López)</author><guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2023/12/do-what-the-community-does/</guid><description>Do what the community does The other day I had a conversation with a team mate about how to implement different patterns to solve a common issue in a interpreted programming language. He was sugesting using a pattern not used at all by the community that indeed was a cool, interesting, and we could argue that it was a more correct one. I was against that.
Humans are gregarious and tend to form communities &amp;hellip; even programming language communitites!</description></item></channel></rss>