<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>project on Diego J.'s Software Tar Pit</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/tags/project/</link><description>Recent content in project on Diego J.'s Software Tar Pit</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><managingEditor>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-L贸pez)</managingEditor><webMaster>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-L贸pez)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/tags/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Asking and receiving feedback on your software project</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2021/07/asking-and-receiving-feedback-on-your-software-project/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-L贸pez)</author><guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2021/07/asking-and-receiving-feedback-on-your-software-project/</guid><description>Introduction A month ago I asked the HN Community for some feedback about my project: Gelidum.
The experience was very positive and I have learned that asking for feedback in a software project is crucial.
Why feedback is important? We know that feedback is important because it gives us a different point of view about a matter or in my case, a project.
But, feedback is not limited to giving different points of view.</description></item><item><title>Immutability</title><link>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2021/06/immutability/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>diegojromerolopez@gmail.com (Diego J. Romero-L贸pez)</author><guid>https://diegojromerolopez.github.io/blog/2021/06/immutability/</guid><description>Introduction In this post I will explain the rationale about working with immutable objects and will present a personal project I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on the last few days: Gelidum.
La nevada by Francisco de Goya
Why immutability? Nowadays, most processors have some kind of parallelism or concurrency embedded in themselves. Single-flow-execution software is limited by the lowest speed unit in the system. There are some solutions that try to hide the wait for these slow sub-systems by computing in other execution-flows (threads or processes).</description></item></channel></rss>